the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right let's not get too crazy in
here um
welcome to the stoa everyone uh peter
limberg the steward of the stoa
place where we cohere and dialogue about
what matters most at the nice edge of
this very moment
last session with daniel schmuckenberger
sensemaker in residence for
october digital porch we all sit on
the digital colonnade and the porch and
just chat
and have conversation with daniel um
so far it's been uh kind of like
anything goes but we're kind of refining
the frame each time
uh so how today is gonna work uh throw
your questions
in the chats in a moment uh i'll tell
you when and then i'll call on you yummy
yourself ask your question daniel
um if you don't want to be on youtube
because this will be on youtube uh let
me know that
and i will read on your behalf so
daniel's gonna um
set the frame uh for today um
he mentioned it last time but we're just
going to repeat it again and then uh
start throwing your questions in the
chat
and we'll go from there so daniel i'll
take you and my friend
i think you can meet yourself now let's
see
you look like you're in like a
mastermind boardroom and you just kind
of like
erased all your your uh formulas for
yeah there you go
all right good to see everybody and i've
enjoyed the
three conversations we've had so far and
this is the
last one of the series and
yeah i the you know original inquiry was
could we uh address
questions and so i was happy to do
questions of any type and it's
just in clarifying that a bit it seems
like
the main interesting intersection of
questions that happens to be possible
here in novel is not
just asking about how do we solve world
problems
or just asking how do we develop our
selves for
personal developmental reasons but at
the intersection of the development of
ourselves
in relationship to and service of what's
going on in the world and what the world
needs
so you know there's one that just asked
the world question is like well how do
we solve multi-polar traps let's take a
specific example what would a good
economic solution be
but people ask questions in here more
like how do i learn more about the kinds
of game theoretic considerations to
navigate multipolar traps without being
corrupted by it internally it's like a
development in the presence of world
dynamics
so i think the i think the intersection
of those questions is really
fascinating i like i care about both of
those spaces independently but
particularly the intersection of them
and it seems like the stow is uniquely
well suited for that so
just clarifying questions about and
personal development means the
development of the person not just
what seems like psychological well-being
but cognitive development skill
development network development whatever
uh so yeah i'm i'm interested in
people's questions and inquiries in that
space in particular
right so boom uh start throwing your
questions
in the chat right now um you know take a
breather
maybe settle in and then people just
bombarding questions already
and just kind of feel into it uh and
i'll i'll take someone in a moment
let's see if i can start off with a
question um
related to the stoa and personal
development
and my personal development regarding
that
i'm finding all the challenges coming up
here
is really serving as like a force
forcing function to practice my stoicism
and becoming more virtuous which is
quite cool i didn't really expect that
um and one
challenge or theme that has come up and
i feel like it's going to come up more
and we we talked about it before on
whatsapp is kind of
unhealthy parasocial relationships and
how people can
start uh getting fixated on you
um because you're in broadcast mode and
whatnot and
i wrote this entry on kind of
culticulture and that kind of hit i
put like some people secretly want a
cult
um and they want to project things on
you uh
and i wonder how you deal with that
because yeah i'll just say this um this
session in particular this series
has the most people reaching out to me
uh requesting things
uh like oh you should do this you should
you should do this because um
you know you you're pretty popular and
then your youtube videos at least on the
stove i have more than most people
um and so i wonder how you you deal with
it personally and if you have any advice
for me or other people at the stoa who
are increasingly becoming a more public
figure
and want to do good in the world at the
same time
this might not be obvious to everyone
since i've done quite a lot of
speaking publicly on podcasts and
various things but i've never liked
public speaking
i actually particularly don't like
attention on me as a person
and so i
just avoided it for a very long time and
tried to
work through channels of influence that
were
less public and
i was particularly bothered by when
people would focus on me like even this
question as opposed to focusing on the
topics that i was interested in
and there's actually a certain point at
which i just had to accept that that's
going to happen to a certain degree and
not be too bothered by it um
if sharing publicly is useful and
you know both work to encourage people
to focus on the topics rather than
personas but also not let the aversion
to that get in the way of sharing things
that can be useful
um
i think if someone is coming from the
other place of having
kind of desire for it more than a
version there's slightly different
things to
uh work with i will say if there's
anyone who
is kind of excited to share things and
be well known for them
it's just less fun than you might think
it is
to have lots of
people uh in a position to either
have hope attached to you that you have
no ability to
really do anything about and then other
people be able to strawman you that you
can't address all of those things like
it's yeah i would i wouldn't say that's
a particularly fun thing
um
and the other thing i'd say is the
the degree to which somebody actually
cares about
anything right they have some basis of
values and
um integrity the more incongruency is
painful
and so then also the more reflective
they are and notice the incongruency the
more kind of intolerable it becomes
so peter when you were saying as you're
here sharing
these things you actually feel kind of a
impulse to
practice and embody the things that you
believe more because you're holding the
space for other people to do it
uh i think that's actually one of the
cool opportunities
i you know there's this perspective that
says heal or heal thyself like get your
own straight before helping anyone
else and there's truth to that
but there's also truth to in the process
of helping other people
uh there's a kind of learning that
happens
in sharing and facilitating and teaching
that is different
than the learning that happens just on
the other side of it pedagogically the
whole
uh learn to teach model as part of
learning
is is very interesting i've noticed a
lot of people who became
therapists actually became therapists
because at least in part as they were
helping other people
develop psychologically they were
gaining continuous like
instantiated nuanced insights about the
nature of the psychology and other
people and it really helped them in
their own reflection and growth
so that's interesting
how do you relate with impression
management and um
like doing good in the world um
in a broadcast medium uh where you're
sort of like
there's an avatar view gets created in
the spectacle
how do you relate to that avatar because
i know i know you seem very
careful about what you say and you want
to know your audience
in case any kind of information hazard
kind of gets unleashed or something like
that
so i'm curious how you relate to your
own impression in the spectacle
in a way obviously that kind of informs
me and other people who are
putting themselves out there
yeah i mean if you have a clear sense of
why you're sharing something publicly
you have a sense of what the positive
opportunity associated that you care
about
is um you know there's kind of a swot
there's a there there's some thread
reliability associated with the
opportunity
and you just think through that and so
for instance talking about
catastrophic risks because you mentioned
information hazard
if people don't understand the reality
of catastrophic risk then there aren't
enough people who care to work on
hopefully solving it so there's benefit
to try to help more people understand
how eminent catastrophic risk
possibilities are
and yet if you get so detailed that you
start saying okay
let me give you examples of very
specific
types of terrorist attacks that are
possible in specific fragilities and
supply chains
you're actually helping a lot of people
who don't understand how to cause
problems understand how to cause
problems more
with that research so there's a direct
info hazard so it would have the benefit
of motivating some people would
also have a risk associated so there's
definitely responsibility in
considering those things and
typically like there are some people
whose work is as a public intellectual
where their public sharing is the main
method of contribution but i think more
often what's
effective is that people have projects
that they're working on
to try to benefit things and the public
sharing is it
is adjacent or you know facilitating
something associated with that
i don't think i would think doing this
is very useful
by itself like it's not hopefully it's
not totally useless
but um
there's a lot of people who i work with
right now in projects who i found
through these mediums
right there was putting some information
out and it served as a kind of
bat signal or a tractor dynamic they're
very useful to projects that have theory
of chains that i really believe in
and then to the degree we want to
actually launch projects that need some
public traction
having groups of people that are in
similar conversations that weren't
happening that get to be
a place to advance certain kinds of
cultural
projects and movements is useful so have
to think about
the public sharing as part of usually
more integrated
strategies great thank you
um so i'll start searching for some
questions that are at that intersection
but benita roy
privately messaged me a question that's
her secret technique to get me to choose
her
um benita uh i really like your question
if you can meet yourself and ask it too
daniel
daniel oh let me get this
hi daniel um
yeah so you know i want to know like
like
who are your mentors that's kind of like
elders from you to elders but also
like who are the young people that you
think are
emerging like you know like
like they're not there yet so you're not
gonna maybe
uh advocate for their whole uh
their whole view but like where where do
you see something
emerging that seems um
like something possible that hasn't been
possible before like
like in what fields or what individuals
and
and again like these are half-born
thoughts right if you're looking at
young people or
these areas and then you just i'm going
to
throw this on this because you said
you're looking at people who have
interesting theories of change and i was
just wondering
who the who they were
thank you yeah um
mentors i've
i feel like i've always been fortunate
to find and be able to interact with
really good mentors and
there's so many topics that i know are
really consequential that i'm interested
in that i don't have
really deep expertise in and one of my
fastest ways to try to get enough of a
sense that i can navigate it
hopefully uh competently
is to find experts in the space that i
think are earnest and really care and
particularly find
multiple of them that disagree on
critical things and so then
i'll reach out to them and really try to
understand
uh have them guide me through the basic
understanding of the topic
and what they think are the foundational
truths how they're forecasting it uh
those types of things
and then also and why the field is
consequential what they think is
important that everybody's getting wrong
you know those types of things and then
where people that i think are earnest
and smart good thinkers who've spent 10
20 30 40 years working on a topic and
i'm just not going to be able to catch
up with that where they disagree
and is it because they're looking at
different data
because they're coming in with different
epistemologies because they're weighting
the data differently
using different models and
if if i can understand where they agree
what is seen as common knowledge where
they disagree and why
then i start to feel like i'm getting
some sense of how to navigate it then i
want to see what would it take to
bring about agreement right bring about
consilience
so i have like i actively seek out
people
who i think have good expertise in areas
of
history and various sciences social
sciences whatever
and have been fortunate to have a lot of
them willing to spend a good bit of time
like educating me i just got off the
phone with someone that everybody here
probably knows jim
rutt and he is
um you know providing ongoing advice
from a kind of
ceo coaching point of view to what we're
doing with consilliance project
um and we have a we have a bunch of
really great advisors that
are providing advice in everything from
technical to communications to brand
strategy to the experience of what makes
a good online forum in terms of the
digital architectures and moderation
and things like that
i was just on a great call yesterday
with a
guy named gilbert morris who should come
on here at some point
who i think has one of the more novel
and really nuanced perspectives on the
history of
uh race and slavery and the situation in
the us and kind of a third poll that is
neither the pro or anti-critical race
theory that
that i think could actually further and
so i've been
um you know kind of diving deep with a
bunch of people
uh he's one of them to understand those
issues more
from really different perspectives
perspectives of people who grew up in
africa who grew up in the caribbean who
grew up in
you know u.s and europe and studied it
from different perspectives
so mentors uh a lot
and i don't require that i agree with
everything to take someone as a mentor
and i also don't require that i agree
that i
would take them as a mentor in all
spaces to take them as a mentor in a
space
i think when we're young being able to
get holistic mentors
that are more like parents is easier as
we
go on you know being able to find
someone that you can really take their
expertise in a domain
and not reject it because you really
disagree them in some other space is
important
in terms of uh
what seems promising in terms of younger
people
it's interesting to watch like the way
the rationalist community
started to have very
very informed high quality conversations
where the people were
actually quite well self-educated and
were thinking about epistemology and
formal logic
and good faith dialogue and then where
they actually started to get to the
limits of pure rationality and starting
to think about symbol grounding issues
so then they started like circling and
getting into different aspects of
other intelligences i i think that's
kind of interesting
um and
i think there are some people who like
we focus on
the downside of being a digital native
and growing up in a digital environment
where you get
false intuition you don't get an
intuition that is kind of conditioned on
physics but on somebody's manufactured
physics
that's true and that's the more
widespread thing but there's some subset
of digital natives that got
kind of very epistemically oriented who
are just
amazing at online research and
specifically the open source
intelligence field
um they're really exceptional being able
to do
scrubbing of large amounts of data and
image recognition and things like that
and that starts to offer some way to
counter the asymmetric info warfares
that are out there
so i find that very interesting seeing
things like
what aubry tang and friends in taiwan
are doing with digital democracy
and how to kind of counteract
misinformation and do
better sensing and participatory
governance i think that's quite
interesting
so i think there's a number of emerging
spaces that
that i appreciate um and some of them
are very different if you take kind of
the
the um you know ascent
space and then you take the like
permaculture intersects with psychedelic
space
um there's some intersection those are
quite different but there's
and there's some really kind of
significant omissions or flaws in each
of them
and some gifts the fact that some of
those spaces start having an
intersection is actually promising to me
and that's the kind of meta tribe thing
that's being explored here which
i really like it's why things like the
intersection of thinking about macro
systemic issues and
and how we personally and as a group
relate to those is something that i
am hopeful for and then the last
question you asked was theories of
change
um yeah that's
that's like a big thing i'm working on
and and
you happen to say that you were looking
at some people had interesting theories
of change or something new on the
horizon it's that
i think it's a that's a big deal for me
anyways
yeah i mean this this would easily take
several sessions to try to
say when we think of a theory of change
being good does it mean that we've
mapped the problem space well enough
that we can define a theory of change
that is both necessary and sufficient
and be able to do some proof of
sufficiency
is that what we mean by interesting
theory of change that's a very high bar
and or does it mean that there's
something that from a forward
engineering that's kind of from a
reverse engineering point of view or
from a forward engineering point of view
a theory of change
acts on a certain level of sense making
an agency in a way that both
increases sense making an agency so even
though it's not clear that it converges
towards sufficiency it's increasing its
capacity
in a direction that could converge and
then maybe there's a theory of change
that by itself is not anywhere close to
sufficient but it's really meaningful
and
in connection with a number of other
things could start to map towards
sufficient something working on
governance something working on markets
something working on culture
you know et cetera um
so for i'll give you just a random
smattering of theories of change that i
think are at least well informed that
friends of mine and adjacent spaces are
working on
that are not like commonly talked about
so if you look at the way that the
economy
has shifted recently
to have more winner take all orientation
than it previously had
and small businesses closed during covid
lots of unemployment happens but the
value of amazon and tesla and kind of
top
stock companies double and um
those types of things and then you look
at
the fact that you know something like
two thousand to five thousand families
own most of the world's wealth
and even though they don't necessarily
own
all the wealth when you factor just
people owning their houses times how
many people there are on land
those people don't control the financial
industry um or the
the underlying um you know financial
markets
so disproportionately to just ownership
of capital is the ownership
of the change in underlying market
dynamics
so when you look at that and you look at
the winner takes all type dynamics that
continue that wealth concentration and
then you combine that with
high-speed algorithmic trading that can
make very fast money on money returns
you combine that with the fact that the
militaries of nation states
can't the really top-end capabilities
they have are weapons of mass
destruction that nobody wants to use so
if you take those away private militias
are basically as big
as nation-state militaries and those are
available to the top
families uh so basically nation state
level military capacity is
accessible for hire and then you take
that they don't have
people that they have to have a lecture
in again and they don't
and yet they can affect campaigns and
elections across countries they don't
have land they have to protect but they
can influence
uh land deals there are a lot of people
that think of this as the new emerging
feudalism the 21st century
kind of feudalism where families start
becoming
more dominant actors than nation states
and so the theory of change being how to
maximally meet the needs of those
families in a way that also influences
them
that what would cause major catastrophic
risk is actually
decrease in security for them
uh like that's that is a totally valid
and interesting
assessment and theory of change
and it couldn't be more different than
something like bjorkman's
um bildung kind of model that is much
more decentralized
bottom-up cultural um trying to decrease
that wealth concentration so there's
like
one side says the wealth concentration
is it's pretty inexorable so really try
to influence the top of the power law
distribution the other side says can we
do a rolling debt jubilee or something
to change that wealth concentration
reboot a new financial system
those are both interesting and then the
question is like
do you run a portfolio of those
strategies is there a way that those can
have synergies with each other
and then when you start to look at
strategies that emphasize something like
market
versus military versus culture versus
state and legislation are there
synergies between those because nobody
can do all that work so they end up
emphasizing a particular subset of
actuators
and yet multiple actuators if they were
in the right synergy become more
powerful
so i'm interested in a network of
solutions that maps to sufficient
not a solution that maps to sufficient
and so i'm interested
in people that can
have really
good faith interactions with each other
to increase the coordination across
different earnest theory of changes
you could be anything thank you thank
you so much
um all right so next up
we'll do ryan you have something about
design principles
if you can unmute yourself
oop how do i start video there it is
hey daniel thanks this has been really
fun um
so i had a couple of questions feel free
to
answer one none or any of them um
and they kind of piggyback off of what
we're just talking about about good
faith
so i'll just read them out what are the
design principles that you
have found most useful when engaging in
collective problem solving
are there criteria that you rely upon to
promote or create
a pro-social environment within which
a group of problem solvers are more
likely to encounter meaningfully useful
discussion
questions potential solutions and
generate working models
have you found that there is a quote
dunbar's number of sorts
for agents involved in collective design
and lastly how do you think about
leveraging
embodiment techniques or ritual to
invoke such a container
thanks so much yeah this great
question uh and if i don't
address all the parts of it come back to
them because they're all good
so when you talk about design principles
there's kind of
the object side which is what are the
design considerations for understanding
the problem space in a good solution
and then there's the more kind of
interpersonal side of how do you get
people to coordinate well to engage in
collective
problem solving and design and i heard
you more asking the second one
um but probably both so i'll see if i
can address them both a bit
if if you haven't had it yet um
having forrest on probably forrest and
zach together to discuss
egp and agp which is something that
forrest spent the last few years working
on as a design methodology for doing
um complex uh
problem assessment and design criteria
to do this thing he calls transcendental
design basically
how do you do design in the complex
rather than the complicated domain in a
way that
maximally anticipates and internalizes
externalities and also has the right
design iteration process to be able to
internalize externalities and additional
considerations that weren't forecasted
so it's both an upfront and an iterative
process
and uh i would say it is the best
process that i'm aware of
for how to understand the problem well
enough
that you get the design constraints to
think through a solution
um and that's the egp part of it the
ephemeral group process
um and i'll i'll just briefly say and
i'm not going to address it at all
it starts with purely questions
um and this is actually a really
valuable insight and just for everyone
to kind of
factor in your own design thinking so
we're before saying okay
we're building a bridge here now we're
going to do a design shop on how to
build a bridge the bridge is trying to
solve a problem
but the bridge might also cause some
other problems which is why if we have a
proposition to make the bridge or not
make the bridge you're going to have
half of people on either side right
very rarely do we have a proposition in
in
a kind of government situation that 90
percent of people are on one side of
which means that most any proposition
that goes through
about half of the people really think
it's a dreadful idea
and so that process itself can't not
polarize a population
and there was i don't remember who it
was but there was some founding father
that made a statement around
uh voting as the death of democracy and
most of us think about voting as
democracy and it's like no no the town
hall where you talk
is democracy democracy the democratizing
the process of input into figuring
something out is what democracy means
voting is what you do
to sublimate warfare when you can't
figure it out
um but the goal in the town hall is can
we all
share our problem assessments the things
that we value the criteria
enough and then be able to dialogue
about this solution and not just yes no
on that solution but that solution is
pretty good for these things but it
caused a problem here what if we do this
right until you come up with something
where everyone's like going ahead with
that
is better than the other options right
and even if i have some compromise the
compromise is better than the warfare
associated with the non-compromise
but if we can't get that we're like no
it just no on that we and so we go
to a vote rather than bullets
then the population will start to
polarize along those voting lines
increasingly so and then you start
getting a situation where whatever
somebody does then in the next term
the other people are trying to undo and
most of the
energy goes into internal friction and
you just can't do when all the
energy goes into internal friction
right and this
is why the combination of a
binary two-party system or a yes no on a
proposition system where half of the
people will dislike anything
combined with a mostly voting and no no
real town hall type engagement
combined with term limits
makes long-term planning almost
perfectly impossible
um because whatever you're going to
implement
if it doesn't create its returns within
the four years you're not even going to
try
and you know whatever you do will be
undone after those four years and
you know so um so that's obviously not
functional and then
and in the business sector it's often an
even tighter it's a quarterly time scale
um depending upon the nature of the
business and if it's private or public
um
so obviously before we have a
proposition that we vote on
we should have some process to say what
would a good proposition be
did we even have a process to figure out
what is everything that people care
about why
some people are saying no to this
proposition other people saying yes
so that we can even do a design process
to come up with a good proposition the
fact that
we go straight to voting on propositions
that somebody makes up with very partial
insights and usually vested interest
usually special interest and we don't
even have a formalized process for the
proposition development like that's so
obviously inadequate
um and so maybe the bridge
that we're going to vote yes or no on
the bridge proposal it's like well why
does anybody want to make a bridge
and it might just be a construction
company wants to make one because
they're going to get the contract and
it's purely
vested interest that just sucks for
everybody well that's kind of worth
knowing right
but if there's a real reason that these
two areas are separated enough that it
takes
two hours for people to commute where it
could take 15 minutes and there's an
economic situation where it really makes
a difference and
so then you say okay the underlying need
has to do with a particular set of
economic needs that are associated with
transportation
it might be that a bridge is the way to
go it might be
that because of the negative
environmental or aesthetic or whatever
effects that that bridge would have
that a ferry is a way to go it might be
a bridge somewhere else is it might also
be that developing the local economies
on each side where the people don't have
to commute is a way to go there's a lot
of other options
once you start to understand what are we
trying to benefit and then what are the
adjacent associated things that could be
harmed by a particular solution
what is this what is the space of things
that we care about
so you have to do some deeper kind of
questioning before you move to
proposal process and
so one of the things that egp does is
get people to really generate the
map of relevant things that become the
basis for design constraints so then you
can do a
design by constraint kind of methodology
and say what is the best synergistic
satisfier we can find
and then you have an iterative process
on that one of the other things that
happens though as far as social cohesion
is people don't polarize on other
people's questions
in the same way they polarize on other
people's statements and propositions
and so if i make a statement that says
we should do this someone can instantly
have a negative reaction
but if someone says you know
i question what some of the negative
environmental impacts of a bridge might
be
everyone can be like that's a fair
question you know i'm a fisherman i like
to
fish i don't want to that up too
bad or whatever it is right
um and so one of the interesting things
is that the
question asking process inherently can
allow dialogue with less intrinsic
polarization and people don't have ego
identified with their questions as much
as they have ego identified with their
solutions
and so it also leads to a
binding of a group in a different way
and not the cleaving energy for the
group there's a bunch of other things
that are involved in this that are
really interesting it also makes
everyone a better sense maker because
if you ask questions and then the
question you ask you have an initial
question that a group of people are
going to be exploring
the first question you ask is what
additional questions would have to be
addressed to really be able to answer
this one well
and then what assumptions are built into
this question and what is fundamentally
valuable related to this question that
we're trying to
understand you get people to actually
become better sense makers
for their day-to-day life ongoingly plus
they get to see
other people asking good questions they
didn't ask that actually positively gets
them to want to perspective seek
so there's a lot of badass design built
into that design process
so that's a few things there now i'll
answer more on the
in a small group of people that i'm
hoping to have be
deeper or longer-term collaborators less
of a society-wide solution
what what have i found helpful to get
people to collaborate well
if there's anything i wish i had better
answers to it's this
uh i can't say that i have had success
here anywhere near as well as i wish
i can tell you some things that don't
work i can tell you a lot of things that
don't work um
i can tell you some things that seem
like they have worked
to some degree and then some things i'm
hopeful about
the more you try to have people who say
are not
engaging because they're being paid and
there isn't a command and control
hierarchy and they're just
authentically coming together to to work
together
the more you really try to accomplish
tangible that way the more you
start appreciating
command and control hierarchy with
people that are paid and the ability to
replace them with other people that will
do a thing because it just is so much
easier
and um and it's important to actually
come to understand why the thing that
has been selected for has been selected
for
to not just have naive ideas about the
other things
so it's good trying to implement some of
the naive ideas and really try to be
accountable for the output and watch
them fail to then come to understand
um
specifically one of the things i found
so interesting is
one of the things that really messes up
deep collaboration good faith
collaboration is optionality
um if i've got some
poor people who all can't afford to buy
their own house
and they're all really struggling and
they decide to build an intentional
community together where the way they do
a land
co-op actually allows them to someday
own something
and gives them more s like foundational
maslow's hierarchy security
those people will put up with a decent
bit of difficulty from each other
and in working with each other to make
the thing work because they have a real
need that needs met that creates binding
energy
that overcomes the cleaving energy
if i'm trying to do something with
people that have already been somewhat
successful in the world
who have the ability to do something at
larger scale all of whom
don't need the thing to work because
they got enough money they can just go
somewhere else if it's difficult
the privilege and optionality that that
creates
makes one willing to put up with less
difficulty
um most of the time so then you have to
say okay well how do i bind myself
to so um
if i got a bunch of people who've all
been ceos or could be ceos
and they can basically be mostly in
control of
and they're used to being effective at
being in control of
they and they can recognize that there's
an upper bound to what they can do on
their own but it's a pretty good upper
bound
and if they come into relationship with
each other they won't have the same
control of
and they optimized to be good at that
for a reason right they psychologically
were oriented to be good at that and
like that
and now they're going to have other
people that have a very deep say in how
the things happen
and um and they're just as invested but
without as much of a sense of full
agency and
like that's that's difficult so i have
found people trying to do
intentional communities or
collaboratives or whatever
um the people that
have what seem like
higher level capacities to affect change
in the world because of what they've
already done
are some of the people that have the
hardest time actually making
meaningful sacrifices because they don't
feel like they have to
um so then
someone has to have
something that motivates them more than
the
seeming comfort of their own life
and that's a nice idea and it's also
hard
this is yeah i know you guys had pat
ryan on before he probably talked about
um blackmail as a currency of
coordination
uh there's always this question when
you're trying to
coordinate where you're gonna share some
knowledge with the people you're going
to coordinate with where if that
knowledge was widely shared you would
lose some of the ability to do the thing
because you're going to corner a market
opportunity you're going to
release some patent you're going to you
know do a military attack whatever it is
where you actually need
some element of being able to control
the information
but you're like the the challenge is if
i want to implement something at some
scale i have to share some information
with some people because i can't do the
whole thing myself
but if i share information with them
that and they defect and share that
information with the public the police
the competitor the whoever it is that
totally up what i'm doing
somewhere between i get put on a bayonet
or in jail or
just become a pariah um or lose the
market opportunity
how do i share the information to allow
the coordination
and protect against defection and in a
government setting
it's you know you take an oath you have
a commander you violate the
confidentiality or the classification
and you get thrown in prison
right you there's a military prison all
that type of thing
in rule of law and generally in contract
law you sign a contract you can get
taken to the court the court will
enforce it
if we're in a gang and this is the mob
and you
snitch on somebody you're just going to
wind up floating in a river
right but if we're talking about
inter-elite coordination where you can't
have the people just wind up in a river
and you also can't use
rule of law because there is no rule of
law for the thing that is happening
how do you prevent defection and so
the idea that having some kind of
mutually assured destruction on each
other
in the in a space that has power which
would be the public sphere which
you know would be something like
blackmail uh that
that that can facilitate coordination
it's not facilitating trust right it's
not facilitating coherence it's
facilitating
anti-decoherence right or anti-defection
but that fundamentally means that it is
like the culture is
intrinsically right the culture
of the thing
is not a trust based but a maximally
guard against non-trust-based
situation so then you have this question
to say if we don't have a place where
rule of law is the thing that we get to
use
and we want to create real trust that
binds people
to to each other and to a mission
where they don't defect under duress
where that would be consequential
and we don't want to do it through some
form of punishment
but what do you do it what creates the
binding energy that prevents defection
under
dress and
you know knight hoods had a model for
this and of course they sometimes would
kill someone for defecting so it wasn't
without the stick side
but the sacred oath where someone
actually had
a sense of what they were willing to
give their life for and that they were
actually willing to give their life that
there was a transcendental
meaningfulness
bigger than their life and then they
could see that these other people
authentically took the same oath and so
that there was something that they they
couldn't defect on each other without
defecting on what matters more to them
in their own life
um and so they have a binding with each
other
that is actually mediated through
whatever the transcendental values are
i have some experience of that working
and i hope to have more experience of
that
working uh as time goes on
um no i don't think it's just enough for
everybody to do
uh ayahuasca together and have some like
nice experience that
that feels very deep because the
question is how does it hold later under
duress
um but you know when you study the
masons and you study the templar and you
study those types of
traditions you're actually studying a
set of social technologies that was
developed very much to do that thing
and i would say most the people that are
working on how to benefit the world
right now are not
studying those technologies and what the
modern applications would be as much as
is useful
and i would say do think about how
people's optionality affects it
that's an important thing um
there's a lot of things i can say having
a culture
inside of a group of collaboration where
everyone
takes more of the responsibility for the
problems on themselves and gives more of
the credit to each other helps a lot
like if that's a cultural value that
everyone
does so rather than have the
status competition of your you're like
hey you copied my thing or whatever it
is
i want to actually whenever i'm talking
and i'm saying something i learned from
you if i can credit you
and i can help i can help whatever your
motivators are where you actually
experience the things you're motivated
by working better working with me than
not
um but where that is symmetric
right symmetrically that's held as a
value and maybe even a vowel
i find those things are quite helpful i
also find not setting them up as vowels
up front and just seeing what do people
naturally come in with
what is the disposition that they hold
because if they don't already have that
disposition they might not even be able
to
or want to be bound to it by some
agreement
so to some degree simply observing where
people are coming from first and not
moving too fast
is helpful we could we could talk a long
time on this one
ryan did you have a follow-up i don't
want to take any more of your time that
was just
really really fun yeah that was that was
great
uh maybe if you could just talk to
embodiment principles or techniques
uh not ayahuasca ceremonies that maybe
uh help with group coherence
i'll share something uh
that forest could expand on again
um i don't know if people here have how
many have
basic familiarity with some of the
concepts in the eminent metaphysics
the domain of the eminent the omniscient
and the transcendent
uh i won't belabor this long as i don't
have the time to explain it
but if you do have the familiarity
there are types of bonding and coherence
in each of those domains
and one of the things i would say is
that it requires bonding in each of the
domains so when you say embodiment
you're probably mostly talking about
coherence in the eminent domain
and this is
this is everything from
um a tribal practice of dancing together
uh in a drum circle around the fire
before making
before tribal council and making a
decision there's something very profound
that happens in that kind of ritual
because
in the drummers are both doing their own
thing
and being in sync with each other right
they're all kind of following a base
rhythm
but they're also doing their own thing
so there's a balance of agency and
communion if they start doing their own
thing that is
out of beat it'll sound really shitty
and everyone would be like what are you
doing
but for them to kind of improv so
there's a how do you find individuality
in a way that also has harmony and the
dancers similarly are all doing their
own thing
but to a similar beat right so there is
a
but maybe some are on the half step and
some are on the double step and the
so there is a way that there is harmony
between everyone
with with individual expression and that
that can create an embodied experience
of like oh we
we have some deeper than semantic level
of connectedness and familiarity with
each other then we go into the tribal
council we're going to talk through
something and we're bringing in
a sense of positive bonding with each
other plus coherence with each other
right
coherence and the eminent whereas
coherence in the omniscient
in the cognitive would be like logical
congruence are we factoring the same
data do we have the same waiting
algorithms on it are we using the same
propositional logic
um but
eminent coherence can also be doing barn
raising together
which also means build a burning man
camp together
right the barn raising or the burning
man camp is we're experiencing
actually working together and you get
experience like
who doesn't actually really work
um and who claims a lot of work and
didn't who really does
how does that kind of fix itself where
there is a sense of like oh we're all
in this together working supporting each
other making the thing happen a real
thing happened
and there's a experience of a certain
kind of coherence that happens from
building some real together that
you don't
get from any level of
um psycho-emotional bonding group
therapy or
cognitive work right it's the eminent
domain is a different thing
um so i would say
looking at some kind of
uh can we actually work together can we
find coherence and work together and can
we sync together
in some kind of fundamental and embodied
ways
then can we find logical congruence are
we running similar
axioms and epistemics and in a
transcendental way are we oriented to
similar values
do we have a similar kind of set of
transcendental values that we're
oriented towards
that there need to be some practices in
all three of those areas
for it to really be effective
all right beautiful um
and we actually do have forests coming
in tomorrow maybe i'll just plug that
right now while it's alive
at um 3 p.m eastern time margaret and
myself are going to have a discussion
with him on the
ephemeral group process so that's pretty
cool and also that
blackmail guy pat ryan uh he's going to
be in
this friday for another session of the
dark stoa so check that out
um a question uh from kerry above
on the ethics of a vegan diet uh if you
can
meet yourself and ask your question i
copied and pasted right here in the
chats
hey danielle thank you um
so i heard you speak uh in an interview
i think it was about six years ago
on the ethics of a vegan diet um
i'm a nutritionist and so i've thought
about food quite extensively for
20 years or so um so
it's interesting to me because diet
seems to be at the intersection of
personal choice
and personal impact and community global
and civilizational impact
uh with 2.6 million years of human
species eating meat it seems like we
carry a biological imperative to
some amount of animal for our best
health
um and i heard you speak something about
like
acts thinking about it really carefully
and educating oneself
on how to eat a vegan diet well and
algaes and different things but i see
accessing these things is somewhat
challenging not practical for everyone
potentially even privileged um so how
can we move out of the nightmare of the
commodification of animals but still
meet our
omnivorous needs
this this is one of the trickier topics
um i kind of wish
that you didn't bring it up because it's
very hard
to feel like we can do any justice to it
in a short amount of time
because the science itself is actually
very complex in the formal sense of the
word complex
meaning what metrics do i pick to
measure health
and which of those are differentially
benefited more by different
diets and did i control properly did i
control for other environmental factors
and con commitment factors and genetics
and
and so you'll have a china study and
then you'll have a refute to china study
and then you'll have an atkins study and
then you'll have a
and while i have seen some comparative
nutritionists
try to look across those data sets and
compare them well
i have not seen epistemics that i
consider adequate
to the problem space yet
so when we're talking about
ethics obviously there's going to be a
what is actually possible and what is
actually true
objectively that is going to be a part
of that if if people really can be fully
healthy
without eating animal products or they
can't be the ethics of it is totally
different
right and
then you have things like short term
versus long term
and how long did the study run for and
does it you know change over time and
and different genetic backgrounds and
microbiomes and whatever
and so i think the complexity of the
sciences
is trickier than almost anyone i've ever
talked to acknowledges
because like people coming to the issue
of race
they come from either that they've been
absorbed
in critical race theory in the
associated histories or
the almost opposite kind of the social
science and so the preponderance of what
they've been exposed to makes them feel
more certain
and the view that they've had of the
other side is usually their side
debunking the other side
and so to the degree that a topic is
polarized is the degree to which even if
people are familiar with both sides it's
through bias that they don't recognize
that's really tricky
and i think the way we feed ourselves is
so
primal right like one two three five
times a day i'm gonna be doing this
thing
so somebody telling me how i should or
shouldn't feed myself
and it goes against my culture my early
childhood my sense of sovereignty my
like it's such a big thing and and on
the same time the
it's kind of the thermodynamic basis of
our impact on the planet
right as a species is that thing and
there's so many of us
that the the net collective consequence
of it is so important to consider
where you can't take a purely
individualistic approach without kant's
categorical imperative does this work
for everybody and
so i think it's just an authentically
tricky
topic so i will share
a couple high-level considerations
so i became a vegetarian when i was a
kid when i was nine
um saw a factory farming truck
it was a kind of horrific scene
red diet for a new america got into pita
and
animal activism and like that and then
when i was a teenager became vegan
i just hadn't studied the dairy part yet
and
i i have been up until now i'm 40.
and i'm you know my blood labs look good
i lift weights you know i
i'm in good health my energy is good so
uh that works for me and i have
tested at different times to see am i
missing something where i don't have a
good
reference so let me take a
you know some small amount for a period
of time uh
eggs or whatever it is that would be the
test of the nutrient i might be missing
and see do i notice a real subjective
difference i'm gonna have a very hard
time noticing an object of difference
especially when
the blood labs are already in a good
range
and i personally have not
noticed a difference and i have noticed
many people who have
and i've known a number of people who
have tried to do
uh vegan diets and were much healthier
for some period of time
oftentimes because it was the first diet
that they did really thoughtfully so it
meant that they just cut out
a bunch of refined food and grains and
whatever
i find that actually most any diet works
for somebody at first
if it is basically a movement from
something like shitty unconscious
standard american diet
that if it's in the direction of cleaner
more whole foods more organic
whether the macros are mostly fats
mostly protein are mostly carbs they're
going to do better than they did on the
like
sugar and hydrogenated fat diet
and usually any of them that they go to
they'll have some more consideration of
calories and micronutrients and some
basic things like that
i find that there's a lot of diets that
people do well on for a short period and
then badly on
like too long on keto or too long on
adkins
or for some people too long on vegan or
for most people too long on fruitarian
where
the imbalance in macros and the
associated imbalance and micronutrients
that go with it end up becoming not good
long-term fits
i think realizing that most people in
our evolutionary environments
didn't have access to the same type of
food all year round before agriculture
makes it pretty clear that dietary
flexibility is the thing that was our
primary evolutionary environment so
we would have had some times where there
was more animal products
less animal product different kinds of
uh vegetation but never like
as much salary as we want all year round
or as much you know like that just
that's a that's a weird thing and so i
think that creates
metabolic inflexibility microbiomic
inflexibility
things like that
i think as far as the ethics goes
i don't think that anyone puts forward a
reasonable case for why factory farms
are a good idea
or an ethically reasonable idea
ethically
environmentally health-wise or any other
wise i think it's one of the like
obvious great blights on the world
and one of the things that i'm
i get sad about so i have friends that
are
vegan for ethical reasons and i have
friends that are hunters for ethical
reasons both of whom i respect
because they're if they're in a real
earnest inquiry around what is true what
is effective how does
their choice how would it portend for
eight billion people doing that if
they're really in it
i don't think that anyone can claim the
basis of authority to say you have to
come to this conclusion or you're
a bad person uh so i mostly care about
the depth of earnestness within
with which one is inquiring and
practicing
but sometimes i will see people go from
say a vegetarian
conversation to a a conversation where
it ethically makes sense to eat animal
products for them because they think
that we can't get heme iron or
b12 or evolutionary environment of
omnivore
or whatever it is they have some
argument like that
that would justify going in bow hunting
or something
but because of that they just slide to
animals or in rather than out and
they'll eat mcdonald's
and i think that is super sloppy
ethically right so how much meat does
somebody need to eat if they feel that
they need to eat some and how was it
sourced
is really important not just a binary
it's all in or it's all out
right i think
if someone
has endeavored to apply a vegan diet
well and they have tried to study the
nutrition of it and they
don't feel that they can be as healthy
then there's a very
straightforward ethical conversation
around it's not causing
unnecessary suffering to kill some other
life
because they are in some ongoing degree
of suffering by not doing it so now
we're
weighing sufferings and now we're in an
in a
authentically difficult trolley problem
right but we're in a real ethical
problem as opposed to just a black and
white it was unnecessary suffering for
no good reason
um of course there are heaps of
questions under this around
but how do we know what the subjective
experience or consciousness of an animal
is compared to a plant and
i address some of those in that dialogue
that you saw and that takes a little
while
um and i i wouldn't consider
the same type of proto-qualia for a
blade of wheatgrass as i would for
a redwood tree like i think those types
of categories are also nonsense
um or obviously for a clam as for a
chimpanzee in the domain of animal
um
when we think about
when we think about the fundamental
principles of ethics one of the
uh this again a lot of things forest did
a very good job formalizing
the ethics of continuity and the ethics
of symmetry is a really nice formal our
way of framing up ethics writ large
ethics of symmetry is one of the main
ways we think about ethics
which is do unto others as you would
have them do unto you
or um rawls is original position
right you design a society
but you don't know which of the roles
you're going to be put into and design a
society in a way where you'd be okay
being put into any of the roles
and make sure that if you design a deal
with somebody that you'd be willing to
take any side of the deal
um pie slice theorem i can slice the pie
but you get a pick
or you can slice it and i pick but i
don't get a slice and pick
so these are ethics of symmetry would i
trade places do i
actually feel that the thing i'm dealing
is fair
not in a sense but the embodied
sense i trade places
so if we extend that to animals as
sentient creatures and say would i trade
places here
if people aren't asking that question
i don't think they have contemplated the
ethics yet
and and asking
the way we design a system for say
a species right cows or chickens in
relationship to humans
from rawls's point of view would i be
willing to be put into the cow place
there or in the human place and say like
that's actually a reasonable
position or did i design something were
there positions i totally wouldn't want
to be put into it's some form of
um you know what we would consider
abject slavery or something like that
so i think thinking through that is
important
and so the hunters that i
respect have a complex relationship with
killing every time
like they have some basis by which they
feel like that is actually
you know there's too many deer in the
area because we've killed the apex
predators in the area they're actually
helping to balance the environment
getting that there
as opposed to factory farm meat is
better even as opposed to agriculture
that's coming through conventional
agriculture producing wheat that is
you know destroyed whole forest lands
that that feels like the right thing to
do
but it also doesn't feel like nothing to
them to kill the animal
knowing that what that animal is
experiencing is a real experience and
what the other animals that were part of
that hurt or whatever
are experiencing watching it and even
more so if i raised it my whole life
right and then
the thing shifts so i think someone's
relationship
with it should be complex
right like i think if it's really simple
it's because someone has actually
stopped wrestling with the wholeness of
it
and if you look at most of the kind of
tribal cultures they had a very strong
no waste orientation right they didn't
take more than they needed
and so in a situation where it's like
we're talking about health but then most
people are obese on the thing
no that's up right um does it
make sense
to take it from much worse sources and
more than is needed in a way that's
actually harming me not helping me
no that's ethically up i don't
hold that everyone sh
necessarily can or should be vegan i
hope that some people can i don't hold
that no
no one can from experience of a lot of
long-term people are quite healthy
um i hold that
everyone can be
much more responsible with their choices
and you know like
also i i try very very hard not to buy
plant products that come from
conventional sources that had damaging
effects on the environment
in the nature of how the conventional
agriculture works so it's not that's
another binary that people do
of like meats in so i'll take the
factory farm stuff
or i don't do meat so whatever plants i
do are fine no
no like the the the glyphosate wheat
that is up the environment or
whatever is actually really bad
um and kills lots of animals and the
nature of how those threshers work and
the
you know field mice and snakes and birds
and pollinators and whatever
um i think it's
hard for us when we're dealing with very
large supply chains that we're
emotionally disconnected from
whereas if i was growing all of my own
food
picking picking a carrot just doesn't
feel the same as slitting a goat's
throat
they don't feel like the same kind of
experience and there's a there's
something that goes with being connected
to that whole thing
and honestly picking a carrot or
wild harvesting a berry doesn't feel the
same
as clear cutting an area of forest to
create row agriculture does
right and so to try to take these very
large-scale things that are invisible to
us
like go to the factory farm go to the
conventional farm go to where clear
cutting's happening go
to the landfill and really get in touch
with what your life is producing
and then say how do i actually take
better responsibility for this
now one can go excessive here and try to
have
not causing harm be the whole thing they
focus on their life will just get
smaller and smaller
because they actually realize if i drive
on the road i'm causing
an electric car versus a gas car my bike
the rubber where'd it come from though
and so that can just shrink you into
there is no way to have your hands
totally clean in a world
that is built on institutional violence
right like it is institutional
structural violence
so there's a certain place where i am
complicit by being in it
it's a kind of ethical humility that has
to happen
but then to also say i'm going to
minimize those harms while also
maximizing my capacity to change it and
if i'll never fly on a plane because of
the climate change but that also means i
can't go
possibly influence the thing at the un
or wherever it is that i got invited to
do
then i might be causing less harm in the
moment but decreasing my capacity for a
larger offset
but then again that doesn't just mean
well i don't think about plane flights
at all and i will do infinite amounts of
them because i got put into the binary
category called plane flights are cool
so
i how to really take responsibility for
the things that i'm affecting but i
can't tell i'm affecting
right i can't tell because they're out
of my senses
that's the deeper consideration i would
offer
any follow-up question carrie no that
was
uh really excellent thank you i live at
a regenerative agriculture
eco village and um sitting with
potentially
uh exploring this complex relationship
and
killing a chicken and so
that really was wonderful thank you
all right i'll say one more thing about
that
when i was a kid i uh
really just loved animals and took in
all the sick and injured animals i could
find in our house became kind of like a
animal rehab place for some time and
that also meant that there were animals
that weren't going to get better that
were really suffering that we had to
kill put out of ongoing unnecessary
suffering
so starting somewhat young i learned how
to
mercifully kill something that i
was dedicated to trying to save right
that i cared about
and that's a very interesting process
right vets obviously have to
go through that and typically one
desensitizes when they do too much of it
because
like think about someone who became a
vet because they love animals and now
they're
in a situation where they're just
euthanizing beautiful dogs all day long
because people are and breed dogs
and they shouldn't
um like how do you not shut down
and so i had a process that every time i
killed an animal
i i was
completely tuned in with it right i was
feeling it i was loving it i was wishing
that i had been able to help it more
and i cried every time right but i also
wouldn't
not do it because it needed done so like
you have to both have the courage and
the sensitivity bound
and if you go on either side where you
don't have the courage or the
sensitivity
you kind of fall off the razor's edge
there
so when you have that experience with
the chicken and the community does
that they really just feel and hold the
whole thing
thank you yeah
all right we have 15 minutes left so um
we'll sneak in this question from evan
and then we'll close up
uh evan i pasted your question
below if you can unmute yourself and ask
it to daniel
yeah thank you so um i think a lot of
people on the stoa
might be in a similar spot to me here
and so i'm going to ask this question
kind of generally
um so a lot of us want to spend more of
our time and energy helping to actualize
the sort of non-rival risk systems and
dynamics of the future that
you talk about and um but are also in a
situation where we will be
literally homeless if we don't keep our
day jobs within a month or two
um and these day jobs require us to
spend our time
in a game a or rivalrous kind of context
and um so i i would just love to hear
your take on
how one can actually make moves in one's
life
to um to move into a way of making
one's way in the world for oneself and
one's family making a living in the
world
um without being so
deeply attached and dependent on these
sort of
um you know rivalrous game a corporate
dynamics that that most of us have to
spend you know eight hours a day doing
yeah i get it
the best answer i have isn't awesome
so things that i did
one was for most of my life i kept my
overhead extremely low
and so i did life design that made it to
where i wasn't on the hamster wheel
of you know make a little bit more
and then want to spend a little bit more
on all the things that
society makes it very easy to want to
spend it on that
then binds me to that thing because i
was very clear that i was trying to
liberate my time
and then i sought what are the ways that
i can make
more dollars per hour doing things that
i believe are good
even if they're not the very best things
because i'm not trying to get my sense
of how
my theory of change in the world is
going to ever give me dollars maybe it
will but
i i'm not connected to that i'm not
going to do something high dollar power
that i think is really bad
um so when i was doing construction as a
kid going through college
i remember seeing that uh the
electricians made more than people
framing and i was framing so i
taught myself electrical work and then
started doing that right like i just
kept seeing how do i increase the
dollars per hour
to not increase the total dollars but to
decrease the hours
while keeping the dollar needs more
fixed
and you know then i was
doing counseling work with people and
then i learned that doing executive
coaching was basically counseling that
charged more
and then i learned that strategic
business consulting for businesses made
more
than the executive coaching thing did it
was like what skills would i need to
develop to actually be able to help here
that are also teaching me something
interesting and valuable
and then how do i progressively keep the
hours lower where the rest of my hours
get to keep growing and know that it
won't happen that instantly like the
development of right
profession is as you know it's a
developmental process years
uh and if someone
now i mostly never had a job like a w-2
type thing i mostly took contractor type
positions
where i could control the dynamics of my
hours and charge and like that better
not not everyone is
oriented to do that as well
if you're in an eight-hour position uh
and you don't know how to make more
dollars per hour in some obvious way
and obviously taking the time to explore
how to do that is time outside of those
eight hours that you're not trying to
figure out anti-rivalrous stuff with um
a few things i would say
the people who were
under feudalism for most of the history
of the world could never ask this
question
like they didn't have eight hours and
then some free time and some access to
knowledge and development
uh or even the freedom that if they
economically freed themselves they
weren't forced
into some position like it is
even to be in what seems like economic
servitude here have no money in savings
and be you know a month away from
homeless
but to not be working 12 or 14 hours
obligately a day
um is actually a situation that allows
us an upward vector that most people
never had
and most people in the world still don't
have now to say but i'm tired at
the end of eight hours
and you know i i want i like i need to
chill or rest or do something else
that's real and the depth to which we
care about it can motivate
finding more energy
now one of the tricky things is like
what resource do you focus on first to
be able to leverage other resources do i
just really double down and focus
on money making so i can buy free time
and fun projects
or am i gonna really try to focus on my
health so i have more energy so i can
work 15 hours a day
and so i've got a solid seven outside of
the eight that i work
but i'm gonna put some energy into
health to have like the physical
vitality to do that
am i gonna try to double down on my
learning straight towards
you know game b type things
i've never found a good answer of like
the order of operations is really figure
out discipline first
and then figure out money i found that
it's like you level them all up one
notch
and you kind of take a moment you level
them all up one notch and then you level
them all up one notch again
and um
and it's very easy to focus on how we
wish it was that it isn't in a way that
is disempowering that just makes us feel
kind of shitty
but to focus on i just don't find that a
useful focus
to focus on that we actually have some
developmental opportunity and
development happening and then just keep
saying how do i double down on that
is the most useful focus
and then i would say like to the degree
you're in those eight hours a day
can you experiment with game b type
things can you even learn more about
game a by
bringing like not just being there kind
of disengaged but saying i'm going
to move up through the ranks here and
learn how business really works i'm
going to learn more about middleman and
i'm going to learn those things
to just bring more like care and
engagement
to your learning and development i think
can happen most anywhere
when you realize everything's
interconnected then you realize that any
domain of learning can be laterally
applied to almost everything else
um
yep those are a few thoughts so quick
follow-up if i may um
so i i like what you had to say um
i spent most of my 20s uh learning
and being only occasionally employed in
a more contractor-type basis like you
described
now i'm employed in a well currently in
an engineering type
role and i'm starting to feel a pull to
not do that and i remember you said in
one of these earlier stoa sessions that
most people should probably
have a job rather than work for
themselves so i'm wondering specifically
focusing on like
how does one decide um or what is your
advice for someone who is in the process
of deciding
whether or not to continue with a pretty
good job for a pretty good company
that's making the world at least
marginally better
versus to strike out on one's own and
accept the much greater levels of
uncertainty precarious
and risk in the service of trying to
actualize something that you feel that
you've discovered in your heart and want
to share
i won't answer this the same for
everybody because
i think i'll i think a lot of people
kind of mostly just want to live a good
life
and they would like to leave the world
somewhat better than they found it but
they're not
hugely aspirational or ambitious about
that
and that's okay i think that has always
and will
maybe always be the case that that's
where most people are
and so have a job that is doing
something somewhat good
and also allows some free time and some
development
is probably great
if you are
possessed by a need to solve problems
that you can't
not solve then it's a different answer
in which case i would say
i would take a job if and only if there
was
really strong developmental opportunity
in it but not just to maintain myself in
my life but if
i had the opportunity to either learn a
ton you're an engineer and you get
to work with some of the best engineers
in the world and your software skills
get to become epic
which can really help future in
which case when i'm there i wouldn't
stay eight hours i'd say 12 hours
picking those guys brain doing
additional and trying to learn
everything i could right i would
actually take the developmental
opportunity
or you have the ability to not just
perfect your craft but
adjacent areas you can move up in
management and other things and learn
how businesses work so that you might be
able to
either launch something or understand
the intrinsic problems associated with
them or
you can grow your network there a lot if
there's very real
return on your time in a developmental
way
then even if the project itself's
output is not all of what you care about
but it's increasing your capacity to do
the things you care about in the future
good um if it's not
i would rather
get a van be homeless decrease my costs
figure out how to do a little bit of gig
consulting and
find something better and get off the
hamster wheel
thank you yeah
all right um we're gonna land here
daniel any closing thoughts um like
anything that came alive from this
session or the series
as a whole
i really liked all these questions
uh some of the questions like i said i
wish we didn't ask the
diet one because i because i wish we had
i don't know 10 hours to start to
address it
um but it's actually one of the most
important questions and
base of like how do we take care of
ourselves as a human and what's the
impact of that and how do we think
through
that um and how do we come up with our
own
ethics that we care about so much we're
willing to modify our own life without
trying to force that on everyone else
and how do we
feel okay not forcing it on everyone
else if we're so sure it's right we're
willing to sacrifice for it
that's a microcosm of how to deal with
israel-palestine and shiite chuni and
every other major
like that in the world so um
yeah and the question of like how do i
take care of my financial needs in the
world while wanting to
contribute to something else like these
are all
i think every one of these are questions
that all of us have to wrestle with
and how do we
live in this world while trying to move
it towards a better world
and so i'm hoping that the questions
that other people asked other people
found interesting and meaningful
um i would love to hear if people you
know want to write
feedback afterwards of what was
uh
what was both good in this process for
you and what could have made it better
format wise or anything else because uh
yeah i i don't get to talk with people
about these types of things very often
i enjoyed this and would be quite happy
to
do more of it in a better you know in
an even better setting if such a thing
became clear
uh so feel free to put um in the chats
what you got from it maybe daniel could
check it out
um and i'm inspired to because we're
going to launch a metagame mastermind
here at stowe again and we're going to
have crews where we help each other out
kind of source the collective
intelligence to answer these questions
um
so we don't just rely on the guests
coming in to to
drop their knowledge but uh very
grateful for you my friend for coming
and sharing your knowledge and wisdoms
with us i would love to have you back
you may or may not be
uh coming in a couple weeks we won't say
anything about that
but um thank you so much for coming to
the store
likewise thank you peter uh gonna plug
uh
some events uh we got a fun one this
wednesday uh
the problem with the sense making scene
imagining beyond the uh
echo chamber this is with ellie hayne
and tarn rogers john
so these are two insiders of the sense
maker scene and they're going to
critique it so that should be quite fun
and i got exciting something exciting to
announce so i'm going to share my screen
um
boom it is maybe not the end of the
world election party
november 3rd 24 hour event
uh we got wim hof stoic breath trainer
we got election meditation
collective presence in shame
breakthrough boot camp uh socratic speed
dating existential dance party
rap on battle and many more jazzy titles
for you to enjoy
that's gonna be posted tonight on the
stowa website
uh let me stop here i will drop those
links um
there's gonna be a 24 hour zoom or
discord
channel too that we can all chat on to
process
the craziness so i'm going to take in
before we're going to bio break we're
going to have a rap on battles now
so some of you might be here for it but
if not i'll take in
tyson and tyson if you can give it a
quick plug before we go on a break
sure thank you yes wrap on battles is a
space for us to
practice freestyle rap and spoken word
all right as a way of engaging in a
collective inquiry
and practicing dialectic and ultimately
building communitas and it is open to
all
participants and spectators even if you
don't
rap or never rap before that's a little
intimidating you are welcome to come and
play in this space
and i look forward to seeing you here in
a few minutes beautiful
all right so uh thank you again daniel
everyone for coming to the stoa
uh we'll go on a play some music if you
want to leave right now you can if you
want to hang out
to check out rap on battles feel free to
do that but
we will take a turn off the recording
now